[Music]
Stanford
University going Way Beyond the material
of the course but let's just talk about
it for a
minute the model we talked
about had a hamiltonian or an energy
which is just C *
p p can be positive or negative
the wave functions for a given P are
just e to the
IX and there's nothing better about e to
the
Plus ipx or P being positive or negative
they're both uh perfectly acceptable
plain waves but one of them has positive
energy and one of them has negative
energy just reading off here now
negative energy is not such a good
thing in um in the real world negative
energy is not such a good thing in the
real world because if there were
particles of negative
energy the world would be unstable the
vacuum would not be an empty space would
not be the state of lowest energy you
could take empty
space which we can say has zero energy
and then just start putting in particles
of negative energy particles of negative
energy will lower the energy and
anything that lowers the energy tends to
be um favored you can make lots and lots
more and more particles of more and more
negative
energy uh you have to get some positive
energy from
someplace you have to get some positive
energy from someplace but you could for
example radiate photons and at the same
time produce more and more of these
negative energy particles
if there were particles of negative
energy the empty space would just be
unstable unstable with respect to
creating more and
more positive and negative energy
particles you can't you have to conserve
energy so you'd have to do both but that
would happen if there's only positive
energy particles by
contrast there's no way that energy
conservation will allow you to make them
if there are only positive energy
particles and the vacuum has zero energy
it's the lowest energy State and nothing
can happen to it to create
particles so a good stable World
requires all particles to have positive
energy relative to the vacuum this is
not a good stable World okay so what do
you do about it well it was dra who
understood what to do about it but only
in the case of Fons now what are Fons
Fons are simply particles that cannot be
in the same state two of them cannot be
in the same state that's a rule where
that rule came from it comes from
relativistic Quantum field Theory but
it's the same as the PO Exclusion
Principle if you know a little bit of
chemistry you know that two electrons in
an atom can't be in the same
state and you have to fill the atom with
particles of different energies
different uh different states and the
same is generally true particles that
are not that that uh that participate in
a PO Exclusion Principle are called
fans why they're called fans I don't
know I mean they should be called pons
it's obvious they should be called
pons and particles which don't
participate in a Exclusion Principle are
called bons but of course properly they
should be called Einstein on but uh it
was Einstein who first studied
them uh never mind fans and bosons fion
can't be put in the same state bosons
can't so what the said was look I have a
very simple solution to all of this just
imagine that the vacuum empty space is
really a state in which all the
particles of negative energy are present
simultaneously filling up the vacuum you
simply can't put any more in because
you're not allowed to put particles into
the same state but everything else is
empty in fact if you were to say think
about it for a moment let's assume that
the real vacuum is the state of absolute
lowest
energy absolute lowest energy now take
absolute empty space what you think of
as ordinarily empty space is that the
state of lowest energy no I can put one
particle of negative energy in lower the
energy so there's a state of lower
energy whatever state you say I will
find another negative energy particle to
put into it and lower its energy the
only way to have the state of absolute
lowest energy is to Simply fill it full
full of all the particles which have
negative energy in other words all the
particles with negative
momentum sounds crazy but it turned out
to be right but you can only do that
with particles which have the property
that you can't put more than one of them
into the same state if you could put
more than one of them into the same
state there would be no end to your
ability to keep dumping negative energy
particles into the
vacuum all right so this is a reasonable
Theory it's it's a direct Theory it's a
very simple basic baby version of the
direct equation is what it
is and uh it's an okay theory for
neutrinos or for onedimensional
neutrinos it is not a good theory for
photons photons uh are
bons and you simply can't play the same
game if there were negative energy bons
you could simply dump them into the same
state more and more and more of them and
simply destabilize the world so no this
is not a good theory of bosons it's a
good theory of
fans um but that's taking us way Beyond
uh this course this quarters
material we've covered in a
sense a lot about the foundations of
quantum mechanics and very simple
quantum mechanical systems we've covered
almost nothing
about what uh we could call the
applications of quantum mechanics so not
even the applications of quantum
mechanics but studying quantum
mechanical systems we didn't even get to
the harmonic oscillator that's a
disgrace but uh we're not finished with
quantum mechanics next quarter we're
going to do relativity and field Theory
but then we're going to have to come
back to quantum mechanics in order to
study more about the basic uh um
structures that appear in quantum
mechanics so it's sort of embarrassing
to teach a whole course in quantum
mechanics and never get to the harmonic
oscillator but uh that's where we are
so uh you can ask for your money back I
don't
know on the other hand it does seem
people got a had a lot of fun with the
ideas of entanglement they didn't expect
uh such a
uh um a response particularly this and
some of it was extremely interesting and
well done some of the uh chatter back
and forth on the internet I actually did
did follow it and sometimes it was uh it
was generally good and sometimes uh
excellent so I uh
I got some sense of satisfaction out of
teaching
that
um we're going to go on a little bit
today about the Schrodinger
equation not the general Schrodinger
equation but the special Schrodinger
equation that Schrodinger actually wrote
down the connection with the things
we've learned up till now is through the
wave
function and the wave function is simply
the amplitude that a particle is located
at a particular position in other words
it's the inner product of whatever the
state Vector happens to be with a state
of definite
position
and we can also write a momentum space
wave function the momentum space wave
function is just the projection of the
same state whatever it happens to be
onto a momentum IG State IG
Vector the momentum IG vectors and the
uh and the position I vectors or the
rather the um momentum wave function and
the position wave function are related
and they're related by Foria
transform that's the basic structure of
position and momentum if a particle has
more than one direction to move in for
example let's suppose it can move in the
XY plane then you
characterize the position of a particle
by two
coordinates the two coordinates commute
you can measure both the X and Y
position of a particle
simultaneously now is that something
that follows automatically from what
we've said up till now no not at all
it's really an imperical fact it's an
empirical fact that the structure of the
quantum mechanics of
particles only conforms to uh to
experiment if we assume
that the different coordinates the
different um directions that a particle
can move and commute and that means that
the wave function is really a function
not of a single variable but a function
of a collection of variables the
collection of variables being um the
position the various coordinates of the
particle if we have several
particles then the wave function becomes
a function of the coordinates of all the
particles we're not going to go into
that today it's uh but uh I just tell
you that the wave function thought of
the wave function of a collection of
particles is not a function of
three-dimensional space it's a function
of all of the coordinates of all of the
particles in the same way that phase
space the phase bace of a particle is
described by a collection of a large
number of coordinates and momenta in the
case of classical physics the wave
function of a particle is a collection
of the of a system is a collection
of is a um a function of the collection
of all of the coordinates so for example
if you have 10 the 23rd particles s
would be a function of 10^ the 23rd
coordinates okay so that's uh that's the
basic structure and you can go to
momentum Space by fora transform and
write the wave function instead as a
wave function of all of the momenta of
all the particles you can even have
mixed
situations mixed
representations where you may
describe a wave function in terms of the
coordinates of some of the particles and
momenta of the other particles this is
also allowed but uh we're going to focus
on the case of onedimensional motion
again we're going to come back to that
and just discuss the behavior of the
wave function its properties just a
little bit mainly properties of the
shingal
equation first the uncertainty
principle
okay where does the uncertainty
principle come from it comes from the
fact that X the coordinate and P don't
commute Whenever two coordinates or two
observables don't commute it becomes
impossible to measure both of them
simultaneously because there aren't igen
vectors which are igen vectors of both
observables in particular
the igen vectors of X are extremely
different every igen Vector of X is
extremely different from every igen
Vector of P the igen vectors of
X are sharp narrow highly localized
functions in space and the igen vectors
of momentum are first of all complex e
to the I PX but they're real and
imaginary parts are oscillations over
all of space
and so there sort of space
filling uh they're not space filling
it's not that the particle fills space
it's just that the particle is
everywhere equally likely to be
everywhere when its momentum is known so
that's the most primitive observation
about the uncertainty principle if you
know the position of a particle you
certainly don't know its momentum or if
a particle is in a position igen State
it's very far from a momentum IG state
if it's a momentum I can State it's very
far from a position I can
State uh that's the most primitive
version of
it we could say more qualitatively we
can say more qualitatively and then
we'll come to quantitative we come to
quantitative precise theorem in a
moment but if we look
at the wave function as a function of X
and its
relationship by Foria transform
d p over the sare < TK of 2
pi s twiddle of p e to the I
PX and I won't bother writing the other
relationship the other relationship is
the one that writes s of p in terms of s
of
x
uh and just start fooling
around trying to construct side of P or
S of x one from the other by Foria
transform you very quickly discover that
the
narrower the
distribution in
X the broader the distribution in P will
be that's a property just of the Foria
analysis
that the
narrower s of X is the broader s of p is
and vice versa if s of p is very narrow
it means that it's just it's basically a
single plane wave then it's very Broad
in X and so that's a pattern a Foria
transform the
narrower a function is the broader its
Foria transform is that's the
qualitative understanding of the
uncertainty principle but let's try to
do a little bit better let's try to
um see if we can the find the notion of
uncertainty and then see if we can prove
a
theorem okay I'm going to prove a
slightly simplified version of the
theorem mostly because there's just too
much on the Blackboard if I prove the
full General theorem I'll prove a
simplified version of it but the
simplified version of it contains the
basic ingredients all right first of all
what is meant by the
uncertainty in a variable
you have some distribution for that
variable and the first thing to do
before discussing the uncertainty in it
is shift the
axes so that the average of X let's say
this is let's say this is
X so that the average of X is zero you
can always do that whoops if the average
of X is not zero let's suppose you have
some wave function like that xal 0 is
over
here if you put your center of
coordinates over here obviously the
average of X the expectation value of x
will be negative if you put your
coordinates over here the uh the average
of X will clearly be positive and as you
move the origin you'll eventually find
the position where the average of X is
exactly equal to zero so let's uh
simplify our story
by shifting coordinat this is just a
shift of coordinates just shifting our
coordinates until the average value of x
is equal to zero okay so average of X is
equal to
zero
first then what now we've we've done it
with average of X is equal to
zero what is the uncertainty the
uncertainty by definition is the average
of x² squared okay and looking at the
average of
X it's zero because anything on this
side is balanced by something on this
side x is positive over here x is
negative over here so looking at the
average of it the average uh will cancel
if you choose your axes in the right
place but the average of x squared x squ
measured relative to
this located axis here will not be zero
X2 is not zero here X2 is not zero here
in fact X squ the only place where X squ
is zero is right at the origin and so
there's no way that the average of x s
can be um can be
zero in fact the broader the wave
function the larger the expectation
value of x squ will be right that's
clear um so a good measure a good
measure of the width of the distribution
you can call it the uncertainty in X and
it is the definition really of the
uncertainty in X is the average of x
squared the average value of
x^2 with a given probability
distribution given that the average of X
itself is equal to zero that is the
uncertainty in X and it's just called
Delta
x
squared just call it's positive number
Delta x squared and the broader the
distribution the larger it will
be all right how do you calculate it if
you know the wave function very simply
you take the integral
of SAR s of X that's the probability to
find the particle at x times
X2 that's the expectation value of x squ
okay that's the average of x^2
probability to find the particle at
position x * x^2 that's the definition
of the square of the uncertainty that's
the square of the uncertainty of X and
as I say it's defin but it's a good
definition let me rewrite it up
here Delta X and I'll square it is equal
to the integral of SAR
s *
x^2
DX all right now what about the
uncertainty and momentum the uncertainty
and momentum is defined in a very very
similar
way uh oh one other point one other
point this is equal
to
S
x²
s it's the expectation value in the
state s of
X2 thought of as a quantum mechanical
this is a quantum mechanical formula the
expectation value of x² squ that's the
uncertainty what about the uncertainty
in momentum in fact for that matter what
about the uncertainty in anything the
uncertainty in anything assuming its
average is equal to zero is just the
average of the square of that quantity
that's a general definition incidentally
if you uh if you don't want to shift the
coordinates so that the average is equal
to zero you can use another definition
and the the other
definition is that it's the expectation
value of
x² minus the expectation value of x
squared these are two different things
the expectation value of the square of
something is not the square of the
expectation value in
particular if the expectation value of x
is equal to zero it does not follow that
the expectation value of x squ is equal
to zero this is a more general
definition of the square of the
uncertainty in X but as I said you can
always shift your
axes around so that this is equal to
zero and just choose this one
here okay what about the expectation
what about the uncertainty of momentum
the uncertainty of momentum is defined
in essentially the same
way
you can Define it if you like using the
Foria transformed wave function and then
it would just be I'm not going to use
this definition but let's just do it
Delta p^2 would be the integral s
twiddle of
p s of
p time p^ 2 DP this would be the
probability that the particle has
momentum P * p 2 integrated over
P but I'm not going to do it this way
what I'm going to do is just observe
that this quantity over here is nothing
but
s p^ s
s and now I'm going to work in the
position representation we can do that
because we know what the operator p is
when it acts on a wave function s of X
what does p
do what does the operator P do when it
acts on a wave function in the in the X
basis what it does well first of all
whenever you take expectation values or
in a products you have an integral DX to
do all right from the bra Vector here
you have SAR of
X the k side of this is p ^ 2 * s and
what is p ^ 2 p is - i d by
DX I'm using
now that the momentum operator p is
minus i d by
DX and p^ 2 is just minus D2 by dx^ 2
second derivative that's what p^ squ is
you act twice with P once and then twice
so uh this is equal to the integral DX s
star of
X
DC s by DX
squared with a minus
sign the minus sign coming from minus I
* minus
I okay now you look at this and you
worry a little bit
um there's a minus sign here how can the
how can the uncertainty in P be negative
what does it mean to have a negative
uncertainty uncertainty in
p as a minus sign
here what's going on what's going on is
that the integral in here is
negative that's all that's going on the
integral is and how do you see that the
integral is negative you integrate by
parts so I'll just remind you the rle
rule for integrating by Parts is if you
have we're going to use this over and
over if we have two functions f and g
then the integral f d g by DX
DX is equal to minus the integral DF by
DX time G
DX this is true as long as f and g go to
zero appropriately at Infinity so that
the boundary terms don't contribute in
the integration by
parts all right but look at it just look
at the structure of it because we'll use
it over and over you can switch the
derivative from one factor to the other
Factor at the cost of a minus sign right
that's the that's the basic rule okay so
let's this is a second
derivative the second derivative is also
of course a first derivative namely it's
the first derivative of the first
derivative
DCI by
DX Let's uh do an integration by parts
all we have to do is switch the D by DX
to S star and change the minus
sign okay so this
becomes DX let's put the DX over
here the D by DX can switch to the S
star at the cost of a change in sign so
this Bec comes plus and this becomes
dcar by
DX now look what we have here we have d
by DX and we have D Star by
DX this factor is the complex conjugate
of this Factor they're just complex
conjugates of each other and what
happens if you multiply a complex
conjugate a function by its complex
conjugate first of all it's real and
second of all it's positive so the in
Grand in here is positive the sign got
changed to plus and this is most
definitely a positive integral here so
p^2 this is the expectation value of p^
s okay we know the average of p is zero
ah we can always shift p until it is
zero now the real question is can you
have both the average of X and the
average of P equal to zero that's not so
obvious the answer is yes uh you can
always you can always
shift first you shift to x equals 0 and
then you can shift to P equals z uh
there's a trick you know I think I'll
come let's come back to it ask me again
I don't want to get off the track the
answer is yes you
can take a wave function and shift it
both in X and in P until both of them
have average equal to zero we'll come
back to it I'll explain to you why in a
little while but let's suppose we've
done that
okay and let's see if we can
find
a relationship between the uncertainty
and x and the uncertainty and P not not
not a relationship well I suppose it's
called a relationship in mathematics but
a inequality is what I want an
inequality the inequality should be such
that when Delta X small Delta p is Big
when Delta p is small Delta X is big or
better yet that the product of Delta x *
Delta P cannot be smaller than
what than har bar now I've lost har bar
in here I've lost har bar because I've
set it equal to one we'll put it back
later but if you want to put it in here
now we should probably put it in here as
a one over har squared here an harar
squared here and an H bar squared here
but let's not
do I have it in the right place yes I
do but let's work with h bar equal one
and later on when we're finished I'll
put back the uh the dimensional
quantities okay so here we
are what tools do we
have to construct
inequalities there's basically one
there's a zillion inequalities in
mathematics but uh probably the most
famous the most useful and the only one
that I know that's uh particularly
useful is the triangle
inequality uh everybody know the
triangle
inequality some people do some people
don't so I will tell it to you and uh we
it comes in two
forms it's a statement about triangles
of all things what it
says is if you have a
triangle that the sum of any two sides
is bigger than the third side obviously
true right the sum of this side and this
side why is that because the shortest
distance between any two points is a
straight line so the shortest distance
between these two points is this one and
the other two sides the sum of the other
two sides is certainly bigger so if we
have uh three sides that's a statement
there's also another version of it I'll
tell you what I think I'll prove it uh
I'll prove the other version but you
know the other version very well also
let's call this one a let's call this
one b and let's call this one C
okay so
um a +
b is bigger than
C or a +
b is bigger than uh bigger than C bigger
than the size of C okay A plus b is also
by the same argument I mean it is the
same thing is bigger than a plus
b if these are vectors think of these as
vectors here's a vector a here's a
vector uh here well let's put it this
way
um C is not a plus b is it it's a minus
B in this case right um I think I want
to think of it this way a
b
c okay it's still a triangle a plus b is
bigger than C which is the same as
saying it's bigger than a plus
b um let's Square it let's Square it
then this becomes a
squ square of the side of a plus b^
2 plus t a
b is bigger than this guy over over here
but what's the square of a + b it
is a
2 plus b^
2 plus twice the dotproduct of
a where did I get that from I wrote that
A + B squ is just a +
b Dot
A +
B that's the square of the length of a
vector and that's a 2 plus b^ 2 plus
twice the dotproduct of A and
B and so we have now an inequality from
which we can erase A squ and B B squ
from both
sides here's another form of the
triangle inequality
let's erase the
twos and what it says is if you have any
two vectors given any two
vectors here's one vector here's another
one a
b that the
product
of the the length of one of them times
the length of the other is always bigger
there I think there's two disappear
is bigger than the dot
product there's another way to think
about
that what is the dot product in terms of
the length of a and the length of B and
something else what else do you need to
know to calculate the dot product cosine
of the angle so a dob is of course
nothing
but a
b cosine of the angle and cosine of an
angle is always less than one so the
triangle inequality is pretty trivial it
simply says that the magnitude the
product of the magnitude of two vectors
is always bigger than the dot product
between them because the dot product
always has a cosine in there now this is
true for vectors in two dimensions three
dimensions 100 zillion Dimensions it's
even true for vectors in complex Vector
spaces it's just generally true for
vectors in any kind of vector space that
the magnitude
defined as the square root of the inner
product of the vector with itself that
this inequality is true in fact uh uh
let's let's just write it as
A.B and let's Square it because we're
going to use it in the squared form a 2
b^2 is greater than a b
s i just squared uh I I haven't
uh done anything very significant and
that's that's the inequality that we're
going to
use this should be greater than or equal
to yes it should be greater than or
equal to the only time it's equal is
When A and B are in the same
direction right that's right greater
than or equal
to when cosine Theta is equal to is
equal to one all right that's our that's
going to be
our our trick so I don't think I need
this anymore we'll come back to it um
yeah well we
will
kind of looks uh promising we have a
Delta x^ squar here sort of like a s we
have a Delta p^ squ here sort of like b^
s and we want to show that it's bigger
than something all right so the trick is
to define the right A's and B's in terms
of size and x's and so forth and then
just use the theorem but I'm going to
make one simplifying assumption I've
already made two simplifying assumptions
that the expectation value of x and P
are zero that I will show you how to
arrange and that's there's no uh there's
no trick there the simplifying
assumption I'm going to make only
because I don't want to fill up the
Blackboard with more algebra than I need
than than necessary this is something
you can sit down with at home home and
go through it for the more General case
I'm going to assume that the wave
function s of X is
real if I didn't we'd be chasing around
size and size stars and I would
eventually Tire you out and you would
probably lose the threat of the argument
so I'm going to assume that Sai is real
it'll save us some
algebra it's not General but it's very
easy to fill in the steps for complex I
easy but it takes a few more lines and I
just I just after sitting down and doing
it on a piece of paper I just decided it
was too much for a Blackboard
presentation to do better to do it for
the simple case so s is
real okay so here we are we we can get
rid of the size stars
then and
um I think I lost an equation
here using the fact that p is minus i d
by DX we proved that this is equal to
integral the S Star by DX D Side by
DX just remind you just quickly to
remind you how we did it p^2 was a
second
derivative well minus the second
derivative and then we did an
integration by parts to take one of the
deriva and put it over here okay so
that's Delta p^2 and what we're going to
try to prove is that the product of this
times this is bigger than
something product of this times this is
bigger than
something okay and to do so it's just a
it's just a trick now think of a and b
as vectors in fact you can think of a
and b as either bra vectors or k vectors
since s is real it doesn't matter
whether they're bra vectors or C vectors
but here's what it's going to be the one
vector a I'm writing them now in Vector
in bra C notation
the triangle inequality is perfectly
true for bras and KS as well as for
ordinary
vectors all right so the vector a is
going to be described as going to be the
vector whose wave function is not s of X
but x s of
x a is the vector whose wave function is
x s of X in other words it's X operating
on S and B is is going to be the
vector
P Time
s
or basically minus
i d s by
DX when I write equals here I mean to
say that a is the vector whose wave
function is s of x b is the vector whose
wave function is DCI by DX and we're
going to apply the triangle inequality
to that
okay
um notice that with this definition
here Delta X2 is a s look at it the
inner product of a with itself a s is
just the integral of s star s *
X2 so this is
here
a
squar with this
notation what about this one this one
here is
essentially b^
s it's the inner product of B with
itself how come I don't have a uh I have
a minus I d by DX here if I put minus i
d by DX over here I would have Min - I *
- I which isus one how come I don't get
a how come I have a plus one instead of
a minus one complex conjugation yeah so
this is b^2 that's a 2 and a 2 * b^2 is
this right it is also Delta x^2 * Delta
p^ 2 so Delta x^2 Delta p^ 2 a 2 p^ 2
the triangle inequality is literally
talking about Delta x^2 Delta p^ 2 so
now let's look at the other side of the
inequality here the other side of the
inequality is a. b^2 so let's compute
A.B it's the inner product of these two
vectors and then we Square it then we
take its absolute value and square it
because we take its absolute value I
don't have to keep track of I's minus
signs and the end they'll all go away
because I take the absolute value and so
the inner product of a. B is going to be
equal it's going to have an integral oh
one uh one thing I did say that I'm
going to choose side to be real so all
of these s Stars don't matter they're
just s every place you see s star you
can think of
s okay so let's take a. b^2 that's going
to be a which is sign y of x
x I've just written this in the opposite
order and then times B which is going to
be D by
DX as I said I'm not worried about signs
or eyes for the simple reason that in
the end I'm going to take the absolute
value of this so that doesn't play any
uh that will play no
role
uh and let's look at this quantity now
we have a. b^ 2 so I can multiply this
by itself if I wanted to multiply Itself
by itself I could multiply it by another
integral of the same
type y DCI by
Dy this is
DX this is dy but all I'm doing is
writing the same thing
twice so if I can evaluate this I'm also
evaluating
this okay so here's the
trick the trick is to
say the S by the x * s does that does
that ring a bell to you the S by DX Time
s no almost no no no not the derivative
of log would be the derivative of log if
it was in the denominator you're you're
on the right track
though it's the derivative of the square
of s it's 1 12 the derivative of the
square of s the derivative of the square
of
s is equal to twice s d s by
thex so apart from a factor of
two what we have here is x times the
derivative of s^ squared with respect to
X everybody see that yell out if you
don't okay so I can remove this s here
and replace this by S
[Music]
squared and at the same time put a
factor of two 1/2
somewh I do the same thing with the
other
Factor same thing here uh s
squared Why another factor of two which
makes this all together a factor of a
quarter and as I said this is this is
just a I don't even know why I'm doing
it I should just write square but it I
just wrote the square by writing the
same thing down
again
okay
next integration by
parts you have a derivative here it's a
derivative of s squ but it's still just
a
derivative and when you have a function
times a derivative to be integrated you
can switch the derivative to the other
function at the cost of a sign but
really there's no cost in sign because
there's another sign from this one over
here all right so there's no real cost
and sign uh and besides we're taking the
the uh the um uh the absolute value so
this is equal
to integral of s^
squar times DX by
DX and likewise over here integral SI
squared Dy by
Dy DX by DX that's familiar that's just
one and this is just squaring the same
thing
again we are finished we're finished
because what is this integral of one
quarter well forget the quarter what's
the integral of s squ s squ is s star s
if s is real s star s is the same as s
squ what's the integral of s squared one
one it's the integral of the probability
over all space so each of these
integrals is one if the wave function is
normalized we assume that the wave
function is normalized if we assume that
the state Vector was normalized this
whole thing is just one quarter and we
have proved
now the uncertainty
principle from the triangle
inequality that Delta
x squared * Delta
p squar is bigger than one
quarter the one quarter if I remind you
came from two factors like this or if we
wish to just um we can just write this
as Del we can take the square root of
both sides Delta X Delta p is bigger
than
12 now what about the
units X and P are not inverse to each
other so the product of an X and A P
can't be a pure
number what is inverse to an X is a p
over
har so
really this is Delta p over har if I put
back the units or basically Delta X
Delta p is bigger than a half H
bar
right that's this is the
theorem that asserts the uncertainty
principle that the uncertainty in
position times the uncertainty in
momentum is bigger than har
now this would be true for any direction
of space pick any direction of
space take or any particle any
coordinate any generalized coordinate in
mechanics its uncertainty times the
uncertainty in the corresponding
conjugate momentum is bigger than har
bar so that's a bigger than H bar over2
as a matter of fact uh any questions
about the UNC about this particular
version of the uncertainty principle
yeah integration by parts has another
term that I guess integrates to zero
right it's which term well f f the G is
the integral of f * Gus
the
opp let's call it f Prime G Plus G Prime
X
right now if you integrate this equation
right this if you integrate this
equation it says the integral of frime G
plus the integral of G Prime
X is equal to the integral of d by DX of
FG but the integral of a
derivative is just the difference
between the Grand at the two end points
of
integration so this is
FG between the two end points infinity
and minus infinity the symbol stands for
FG evaluated in Infinity minus FG
evaluated at the other end of
integration and what I'm assuming is
that uh that
s goes to zero at Infinity which it
would have to do if it's normalized if
it's integral is finite if the
probability distribution is normalized
it means that the wave function has to
go to zero so this is zero and this is
just a rule that you can interchange
where you put the derivative at the cost
of a sign
right
yeah okay any other question about the
uncertainty principle yeah um you keep
saying greater than but we s than equal
to is it is it a small point or no
um no it's not a small
point when you prove that something is
bigger than something else you can then
ask the question can it ever be equal to
that something else the and the answer
may I mean I you know we may have proved
an inequality which was not the tightest
inequality we could have
proved could have been that somebody
could come along
smarter and
um
proved a tighter inequality that it's
got to be bigger than something else
stronger inequality in this case it's
not true you can find wave functions for
which Delta X Delta p is equal to H over
two so they're called minimal
uncertainty wave packets so it's it's
it's not a trivial
point this doesn't apply to time and
energy
well yeah
it does but the circumstances under
which you use it are less clear and I
don't really have time to explain now we
make at some point in these course we
will probably want to think about it but
do
remember that the time dependence of a
wave function the time dependence of a
wave function s of t as a function of
time is a sum over the igen vectors of
the
energy let's call it
uh sum over all the energy igen vectors
of e to the minus
i e t that's time times the energy IG
Vector times a uh times a um a function
let's call it let's call it f of
e so the relationship between the wave
function as a function of time and the
wave function as a function of energy
is once again you sum up things an
energy with phases like this to get
things as a function of time that's the
for a transform
relationship so it's
um but exactly how you use it is I'll
give you an example of how you use it if
you had some wave function moving past
you it's moving past you and you ask how
long does it take for the wave function
to actually pass you and this could be
Light Beam
incidentally but uh how long does it
take for the wave function to move past
you in other words what's the
uncertainty in the time at which the
wave function might have maxed been
maximum how long does it take the
maximum to get past you that you can
call Delta T uncertainty in time that
the wave function arrived right at your
nose uh it's related to the uncertainty
and the energy of the wave function the
bigger the uncertainty in the energy
well let's say it the other way the
smaller the uncertainty in the energy
the bigger the uncertainty in when that
wave packet will pass you for example
that's an example of the energy time
uncertainty
relation uh
so any pair of things which are related
by Foria expansion and this is a for
expansion it's writing s of t as a sum
or an integral over oscillation
any two things which are related in that
fashion will have a uncertainty
principle there are lots of other
conjugate pairs like
this the
angle of supposing you have a uh a rigid
body rotating about a point with an
angle Theta characterizing its
position then the angle Theta and the
angular momentum have exactly the same
kind of relation
relationship uncertainty and angle time
uncertainty in angular momentum is also
H I think it's h over two also so very
similar kinds of uh
things okay any other
questions
okay let's turn to the Schrodinger
equation
the Shing equation is the wave is the
equation for the way a wave function
changes with
time it also
governs the way expectation values if
you know how the wave function changes
with time then you can try to deduce how
expectation values of observables change
with time one of the things we would
like to do is to see the relationship
between the motion of wave packets
governed by the schinger equation and
their classical counterparts namely the
motion of systems systems in this case
being a particle we would like to see
that as long as the wave packet is
narrow and not too crazy easily spread
out and not you know if it's a nice
bell-shaped
curve that and stays a bell-shaped curve
for for some length of time that um that
the wave function or the center of the
wave function moves in a way which is
familiar from classical
mechanics we need to be able to do that
to make any relationship between the
classical and the quantum mechanical
things that we've been talking about
okay now we talked about this I'm going
to let's
um let's first write down the general
Schrodinger
equation I'm going to take you back a
couple of lectures now take you back a
couple of lectures and um and go
through the derivation of how a wave
packet
moves the answer is the wave packet
moves so that its Center satisfies the
classical equations of
motion uh I'm not going to do that in a
new way I'm going to go right back to
the old way that we've already talked
about and to do
that we first of all in order to know
how the wave function changes we need to
know the
hamiltonian and let's uh just remind
ourselves how it
works the wave
the the way State vectors change with
time
I the side DT is governed by the
hamiltonian acting on
S if we were to take for our
hamiltonian p^2 over 2
m that's the hamiltonian for a classical
particle why we should take it for a
quantum mechanical particle is not OB
not obvious and what what might we add
to that to put some uh to put the
particle in a force field
we might add a potential energy function
potential energy function might be plus
v of
X okay so that would be the classical
hamiltonian for a particle moving in a
potential energy function V
ofx and we can take that we can lift
that right from classical mechanics and
think of it as a quantum mechanical
hamiltonian and then check afterwards is
the wave packet really moving the way
classical mechanics would say say that
the uh that the classical particle
moves okay all right so let's try that
we we
let's we will just work in a little
while we'll just work with this abstract
equation here but let's just uh see what
it
says h on s h on
S instead of working with abstract K
vectors we can work with wave functions
and what this equation would say would
be
I the S of x by
DT is
equal now p^2 what is p p is minus i d
by DX p^ 2 is minus d by dx^ 2 or DC by
dx^
2 there's a 1 over 2
m - 1 / 2
m Time
s but what is V of X is V ofx X an
operator yes V of X is an
operator by definition this is a
definition now I told you what the
operator X does the operator X when it
multiplies a wave
function just multiplies it by
X the corresponding thing for a general
V ofx is the meaning of the operator V
ofx is that it multiplies the wave
function by V ofx
we didn't talk about that much we didn't
talk about functions of X but functions
of X are just defined in the obvious way
as thought of as operators they operate
on Wave functions just to multiply by V
ofx is that because V of X is a function
position yeah yeah functions of
operators yes V of X is a function of
position
X multiplies s of x v of X also
multiplies and you can take this as
definition they um when you make a
definition of course you're later going
to want to prove that it was a useful
definition you not just make definitions
you make definitions and then show that
they uh that they uh either are valuable
because they're easy to work with or
they're valuable because they relate
things to previous things you already
knew what we're going to want to show is
that with this definition of how V ofx
acts that the schinger equation will in
fact make particles move according to
classical uh orbits or at least make
wave packets in so far as they don't
spread too much move according to uh the
uh the classical equations of motion all
right
so that's one term DC 1 over 2 m second
derivative of s
and the other term is just plus v of x *
s of
X when V of X acts on S of X it just
multiplies it and this becomes the
shringer equation this is the
Schrodinger equation for how the wave
function changes with time it's also
Depending on
time let's at the same time
write you know what I want to do with
this I'm going to be interested in DCI
by DT so I think I'll multiply away this
I what do we do we multiply if we want
to get rid of an i we multiply it by a
minus I right minus I * I is is one so
we multiply by minus I that'll get rid
of this minus sign and put an i here and
put a minus I
here
that's side dot if you like the left
hand side is side
dot let's also write down the S
star of x and t with respect to T it's
not a new equation it's just a complex
conjugate of this one and that one will
be minus I over
2m DC s Star by dx^ S
plus
I V of
x s of
X
H I think I got it
right did I make a
mistake everybody's talking at once and
I can oh yeah good side star
good right those are the shinger
equations they're equivalent to each
other I just wrote them both cuz I'm
going
to need them
both
okay now what do we want to do we want
to see how various expectation values
change with time if we identify the
expectation value with more or less the
center of the wave packet
if the wave packet looks like this the
center of the wave packet will be close
to the expectation value and so let's
identify uh the center of the wave
packet with the expectation value and
ask how expectation values change with
time let's see if we can work it
out all right so let's start with X
let's see if we can calculate d by
DT of the expect expectation value of x
and that of course
is d by
DT of the integral SAR of
X X2 no just
x s of
X when you wrote down the D over DX at
the start you said DT DT T by
DT another the velocity of the center of
the wave packet that's all this is It's
the velocity of the center of the wave
packet why does it change it changes
because side
changes how do we know how side changes
we know how side changes because we know
the Schrodinger equation so this is
going to be a little exercise a little a
little bit too tedious for my taste uh
to do on the Blackboard it's not it's
not very tedious but still I'll I may uh
I may cut little pieces um take some
shortcuts but uh I I'll tell you when I
do okay so this is what we want to
calculate and this of course X is just X
it's not dependent on time but SAR and S
are dependent on time so when I
differentiate I could get a term from
each one of these and this will give me
integral the S
star of well let's just write the by DT
SAR X
S
Plus integral s
star
x s
dot right one term coming from
differentiating with respect to Time s
star another one from differentiating s
each one has X in
there and now of course this is just
siar
Dot
all right first thing is we don't really
have to calculate both of these These
are complex conjugates of each other we
have SAR dot here we have s dot here we
have S here SAR here and X is real so in
fact all we have to do is calculate one
of them and add its complex
conjugate that's all we have to do or
equivalently just take twice the real
part adding something to its complex
conjugate the imaginary Parts cancel and
it's just twice the real part all right
so we we can use that I'm not sure we'll
need it but let's uh let's
um let's say it's twice the real part of
this twice this and keep in mind that we
throw away anything that's
imaginary we throw away anything that's
imaginary because we add the complex
conjugate it and that will throw it away
okay so now let's plug
in uh DC Star by DT over here and that
gives
us Min - I over 2
m
DC s well let's see what are we doing
it's plus I'm sorry it's plus I it's the
upper equation there D second s by dx^
2 I think it's minus i v
ofx
s
okay now the first thing we can see
immediately is that the term with v of X
is pure imaginary the SAR there's X the
s s star I is certainly real X is real V
of X the potential energy is real and
there's an i there so the first thing to
conclude is that the V of X doesn't
contribute at
all it doesn't contribute at all because
when you multip when you add the complex
conjugate it will cancel so in this F in
this equation we can throw this away
over here SAR x v of x s that's real
with the imaginary part uh
cancels so we can throw this
away okay next what's the next
step integrate by parts that's always
the next
step it's always the next
step is integrate by
parts we have here
a
derivative it's a second derivative but
a second derivative is also a first
derivative let's write it that way it's
D by
DX of DCI by
DX incidentally partial derivatives have
no well yeah they do mean something they
mean derivatives with respect to x uh
without changing time yeah okay all
right so that's our
equation and now I want to integrate by
Parts which means I want this D by DX
over here to shift to the other
factor I want to shift it to the other
factor and I'm going to get two
terms let's look at what the two terms
are the first term the D by DX will just
hit x what does that give what is d by
DX of
x
one so that will give me twice
integral s star the X will disappear
when d by DX hits
it and there is DCI by DX right DCI by
DX this derivative got shifted to here
there's an I I think over 2 m right
there's an I that I left
out over 2 m
oh what else did I leave
out integration by
parts
minus that's one term
now again you might think this is
dangerous I here we should throw it away
because it's imaginary but it's not
imaginary it's real uh we'll uh we'll
see that in a moment
okay in fact we'll see exactly what it
is in a moment but let's do the other
term the other term has an i over to
m i over to
M uh there'll be an X the X does not get
differentiated now X and then there is
the S star of X now the derivative hits
the S star and we get
derivative of s
star times derivative of
s okay this derivative now hits the SI
star there's an I here an explicit I and
this is to be integrated over X it's
still underneath the integration here
how about this what's the reality
property of this is this real or
imaginary uh it's probably a minus
yeah there is a
minus okay but it's
imaginary this is the complex conjugate
of this and X is real so this integral
here the integral here is perfectly real
it gets multiplied by minus I and it the
whole thing is imaginary it will get
eaten when you add the complex conjugate
so the only thing that's
left is
this I over 2 m with a minus
sign Time s star DCI by DX now I'm going
to tell you exactly what this
is what is minus i d by
DX it's p
right it's p - i d by DX is p so what
this
is is it's the expectation
value of
P divided by m p over
M just look at it d by d i minus i d by
DX on S that's the same as p on S
multipli by SAR that's the bra Vector
integrated over X that's just taking the
inner
product right in fact it's
real in fact it is really real it looks
imaginary because of this but if you go
and study it carefully you find that
it's real and what it is is the
expectation value of the momentum
divided by m so now we've proved an
interesting theorem we've proved
that
DX by
DT is equal to p/
M we've seen this before this is the
classical relation between velocity and
momentum mass time velocity is
momentum now what we found is that this
is going to be a feature of the motion
of a wave packet if we have a wave
packet that moves in a nice way so that
it holds itself
together which it may or may not do but
if it does if we're in a regime of
parameters where the wave packet moves
uh uh like a nice uh nice wave
packet then we will find that the
expectation value of its momentum
defined in this way will be related to
the expectation value of the velocity of
the wave packet through the standard
classical mechanical equation
okay that's
half of mechanics what's the other half
of
mechanics we found that dpd we found
oops I just gave it away DX by DT is p
over M what's the other
half DP by DT that's Newton's law time
derivative of momentum is called Force
so let's see if we can do the same thing
with
momentum question yeah um in your
summary when you know when you said that
if if everything is kind of grouped
nicely it behave that way we didn't take
we didn't have a nicely grouped
assumption in our derivation we or is it
just that that's going to it's going to
look classical if it's nicely grouped
right
yeah there was no there was no
assumption
here there will be as we'll see a
certain assumption in the other
equation no no assumption here of that
type okay
um if the wave packet is really crazy it
might not mean anything very sensible
but uh but still that uh that was a
uh nothing I did up till now depended
on any approximate
notion of how the wave packet
moves okay
we got
this let's see if we can get the other
half now I don't guarantee to be able to
get through it without um
without all sorts of Errors of eyes and
minuses but let's try this
one all
right P the average of p is gotten by
acting with p on S and that's minus I
it'll give us a minus I which I'll put
over here but then d by
DX DCI by
DX we could put the DCI by we could put
the derivative over here by an
integration by parts and a sign change
but we'll leave it over
here D DX H are we looking for
DDX on the very left hand side should
that be
X on the bottom where D DX no no no no
we want the time derivative of the
momentum what do we want to see we want
to see that the time deriva of the
momentum uh is
governed let's write Newton's
equation P dot is equal to force that's
it what is force in terms of the things
I've written on the
Blackboard
minus DV by
DX so this is what we're going to want
to show minus DV by
DX but we'll show it in the form that d
by DT of the expectation value of the
momentum is minus the expectation value
of DV by
DX DV by DX is also a function of x if V
is a function of X DV by by DX as a
function of X it's called the
force what this says is the average rate
of change of momentum is the average of
the force where the force
[Music]
um the DV by DX is minus F okay so
that's what we want to show we want to
show that d p by
DT is DV DX that's our
goal okay and how we going to show it
once again we're going to show it by
using the Schrodinger equation to tell
us
how
uh
how things change with
time okay so let's see now
[Music]
um this may get a little bit unpleasant
let's I'm not sure
right
uh what I'm
debating all right let's let's start
working it out and at some point I may
say well I know this goes away and this
doesn't go away but we we'll we'll see
how it goes okay so first of all this
gives us integral siar
dot time DC by
DX minus I
and then there's another term where did
that come from that came from
differentiating s star with respect to
time then there going to be another term
where D by DT will hit s okay so what
will that be that will be again minus I
integral s
star now the order of differentiation
doesn't matter so this can be written
as uh d by
DX of s
dot I'm just wondering at one point I'm
going to regret not having done an
integration by parts but it won't matter
because if I do the integration by parts
I will reg I will regret it so I might
as well just go
ahead uh is there an extra
I
[Music]
um no I don't think so
so I I don't think so no I think it's
right okay
uh oh you know
what I think it will be convenient to
integrate this one by
Parts if I integrate this one by Parts I
will get a plus I here and a d Star by
DX
here now the reason it's convenient is
because the thing in here is the complex
conjugate of the thing
here okay s do star well that's the
complex conjugate of s dot d s by DX
that's the complex conjugate of s star
but notice it's I times the difference
what do I get when I take I times the
difference of two complex
conjugates real you get a real thing
again all right
so
um I think it's just the real part of
this well let's just keep going my eyes
I I'm let's let's just keep going we can
erase this and remember in the
end that the answer has to be twice the
real part of this
this twice the real part of this and we
don't have to keep track of both of them
okay now what do we do we plug in the
Schrodinger equation and pray like mad
that it all goes
well okay so side dot is equal to I over
m DC
s by dx^
Min -
i v of x
s this I canels this I and gives a minus
sign so this I well there's an I here
this will make
minus and the I over here times the I
over here I think will make
plus plus
okay we have a somewhat unpleasant uh
thing here how unpleasant is it let's
see
um not too bad
uh this piece I believe is pure
imaginary it is it is it is this is pure
imaginary over
here the way you see it the way you see
it is again integrate by Parts just this
piece here if I integrate this piece by
Parts we'll get a derivative we'll get a
term with a single derivative of s and a
second derivative of s
star
okay what will the discover is basically
the difference between a thing and its
complex conjugate it' be a minus sign
okay let's let's let's just see
it um yeah let's just do it if I
differentiate or sorry integrate by
Parts that'll
bring
uh the derivative over to
here it's pure imagin
AR I know that it is whenever you have a
quantity complex conjugated times a
derivative of the unconjugated thing and
you integrate it it's always pure
imaginary we've used that trick before
I'll just tell you right now this piece
is pure imaginary it's not going to be
of any significance the significant
piece
is integral d s Star by DX
v
ofx s that's all that's left after we
take into account uh the
um the little intricate details of
complex
conjugation V of X we d
h
uh I can't remember whether we doubled
it or not yet
um
I think we double it I think we double
yeah yeah yeah we double it we have to
double
this yes we have to double
it or add it to its complex conjugate I
would say right we have to add it to its
complex conjugate I
think in fact let's do that right now
let's add it to its complex conjugate
plus the integral of s
star v
ofx d s of d s by
DX all right I've taken this and complex
conjugated it I've taken this and
complex conjugated it and V is
real okay now we're almost
there we have the SAR of X DX Time s
let's pull out the V ofx let's pull it
way out out here V of
x v of x
[Music]
times this now what is the side what is
this thing here s * dcar of X Plus SAR *
d by
DX it's the derivative of s star s with
respect to
X this is derivative of SAR * S Plus SAR
* the derivative of s that is nothing
but the derivative with respect to X of
s star s so let's put that
in and the next
step integrate by Parts all right
integrate by Parts that'll take the d
derivative over to here and it will give
me
minus the
integral of s star
s times DV
ofx or if I put the S over here on the
right and what is this thing the
integral of SAR s * dvdx that's the
expectation value of
dvdx this whole thing is the x minus the
dvdx in other words it's exactly
this so what we found after a slight bit
of
painful uh integration by parts and a
little bit of algebra and throwing away
some things which I told you were pure
imaginary which they were we find that
DP by DT is exactly equal to minus DV by
DX but in the sense of expectation
values in the sense of the expectation
value now why do I say know um this this
also is exact I didn't do anything
illegal here I didn't do any
approximation I'll tell you where
the use or where it's where it may be
important that the wave packet have a
nice
shape the expectation value of DV by
DX is not the
same as V or
D let's just take V Let's just just take
V the expectation value of of v
ofx no let's call it f ofx Force the
expectation value of f
ofx it's really annoying which is after
all minus DV by DX the expectation value
of a function of X is not the same
thing as the
function
of the expectation value of
x this represents the expectation value
of x the center of the wave
packet and this is a function of the
center of the wave packet it is not the
same thing as the thing we calculated in
general this is the expectation value of
f ofx let me give you an example where
they're very very different where they
they could be extremely
different suppose for example that
F were equal to X x^ squ supping the
force happened to be x s and supping the
wave packet consisted of a pair of
bumps let's see is that what I want I
think that's what I want yes that is
exactly what I want what centered about
zero what is the expectation value of
x what's the what's F of the expectation
value of x
X zero right on the other hand what is
the expectation value of x
squ certainly not zero this one has an X
squ that's equal to the x square of this
right it's certainly not zero so when
wave packets are nice not
nice single bumps which are mainly
characterized by the centers like this
then in general you could not write
that the time rate of change of the
momentum is equal to the force evaluated
at the expectation value of
x it's only if the wave functions are
nice and uh so
that
concentrated over a fairly narrow range
if they're concentrate over a reasonably
narrow range then the expectation value
of f ofx is the same as the ex as F of
the expectation value of x this is where
we have
uh cheated a little bit in saying this
looks like the classical equation of
motion that depends on the wave packet
being nice and coherent and well
localized what are the circumstances
under which a wave function will remain
nicely localized well I'll tell you what
the circumstances are the circumstances
are that the particle is heavy if the
particle is
heavy and takes two things the particle
being fairly heavy and the potential
energy not having too many spikes not
having spikes in it or something like
that spikes when the wave function hits
spikes it tends to break up for example
if you have some sort of wave function
coming in a nice wave wave packet coming
in moving to the right and it hits a
Point structure here what will it do it
will spread out all over the place like
that the wave function will disintegrate
all over the
place if on the other hand it hits a
very
smooth potential of some
sort then it will go through the smooth
potential moving more or less according
to the classical equations of motion so
you know we we don't expect quantum
mechanics to reproduce classical
mechanics in every possible circumstance
we expect it to reproduce quantum
mechanics in circumstances where it
should where particles are heavy and
where potentials are nice and smooth and
don't cause the wave function to break
up into little pieces or disintegrate or
scatter all over the
place okay
um let's see if there are any other odds
and ends that I wanted
to No not tonight that's uh we're we
don't have time for it
um about
describing what sort of physical
situations would correspond to quote bad
potentials that break up the way
fun
well okay
the situation which is bad tends to be
when
um when Delta
when the potential has structures and
features in
it which let's say have some size
associated with them some structure
which we can call Delta X some size
associated with the structure here and
where Delta X is significantly smaller
than the uncertainty in position of the
particle if the structures if the
um what do we want to call them features
sharp features of the wave function take
place on a scale which is much smaller
than the
um then the size of the incoming wave
packet then it will break up the uh the
wave function to a lot of little pieces
each one will scatter they'll scatter
off in different dimension they
different different
directions uh did I write this right
yeah when done that's
right the sit okay let's uh let's isn't
isn't the case then it's in those cases
where in some sense classical mechanics
itself is breaking down is that right
where yes in other words you shouldn't
expect it to rep no no no no you
shouldn't expect it because of course of
course right when there yeah when there
are basically when the fature in the
potential are shorter wave are shorter
than the wavelength of the uh of the
particle it'll break it up into a right
um
now if you were to take a uh bowling
ball and you were to ask what is Delta X
well let's
see
typically
it's true that typically uh Delta P *
Delta X the rule is that it's bigger
than har but in many reasonable cases
it's of order
har now
P that's about as concentrated as you
can get it but for an ordinary
macroscopic object the uncertainty
principle is pretty well saturated Delta
P * Delta X is more or less about equal
to H bar why that's so is a very
complicated question but uh very
complicated now what is Delta P Delta p
is the mass times the Delta
velocity okay so the uncertainty in
velocity times the uncertainty in
position is H bar over
M now if I put a bowling ball down on
the ground you know very well that the
uncertainty and its velocity is not very
big the uncertainty and itsel velocity
is in particular as it gets heavier and
heavier you might expect the uncertainty
and the velocity get smaller and
smaller and in any case there's an M
down
here uh and
so whatever Delta V is as M gets small
as M gets smaller and
smaller Delta X will get bigger and
bigger right Delta X will get bigger and
bigger right and in particular it will
tend to get bigger than the features in
the
uh in the
potential so in a highly quantum
mechanical limit where mass is very
small and Delta X tends to be
big the wave function will move under
the influence of a ragged
potential which uh which it sees as
being being much sharper and much more
featured than the wave function itself
that's when it breaks up on the other
hand as M gets very large Delta X gets
small Delta X will tend to get small as
uh as M gets very large and so for a
large bowling ball the wave packet might
be very very concentrated and when it
moves through here it moves through like
a tiny wave function and the tiny wave
function thinks that these features are
very very broke broad moving through
broad
smooth features doesn't disrupt the wave
function and break it up into
pieces so large mass and smooth
potentials is the limit of classical
physics light mass and abrupt potentials
is more quantum
mechanical yeah just to get a feel for
what you mean by large and small um if
you is Elon large enough to
behave
classically it's an interplay between
the shape of the potential and the
mass if you take a very very
smooth
potential of the kind that you might
make let's say with a couple of
capacitor
plates capacitor plates separated by a
meter well we don't have to take a meter
a
centimeter
with a smooth electric field between
them
then the electron will move through it
uh as as a nice coherent almost
classical
particle on the other hand if you take
the potential associated with the uh
with the core of the of the atom the
nucleus that has a sharp feature in it
and uh that sharp feature will if an
electron wave comes and hits it will
scatter it all over the place so it's an
interplay between the mass and the
sharpness of the uh of the potential so
can you do that experiment with a
nucleus an electron and show that it
actually does be
absolutely
yep and is that what Le let not let's uh
of course you can do it with electron no
problem with electron very easy the
classic experiment was done in
1911 it wasn't done with
electrons it was done with alpha
particles alpha particles come in and
hit a gold nucleus gold nucleus is a
small thing and the result was that the
gold nucleus when the alpha particle
comes in the wave quantum mechanical
wave of alpha particles comes in hits
that tiny gold nucleus and it gets
scattered in all directions
that's why Rutherford was a bit
surprised to see um to see his alpha
particles get scattered right back at
him and what did it tell him it told him
that the nucleus was very
small
right I
didn't
right
he just thought he had a beam of alpha
particles some of which hit the center
some of which went through
here
right but in fact what he really had was
a
wave and the wave came in hit the uh hit
the tiny uh gold nucleus and got
scattered all over the
place and with electrons yeah sure it's
very
easy
that's what happens in accelerators when
electrons hit small
targets they just SC oh photons do
also photons do also electromagnetic
waves if they
hit you know structured objects with a
structure smaller size smaller than the
wavelength they get scattered all over
the
place if they hit very smooth
things they tend to propagate according
to the geometric
optics for example if you have a um a
piece of
material with a position varying uh
index of refraction if that index of
refraction is varying very smoothly and
very slowly over the wavelength of the
photon then geometric optics is a good
approximation if on the other hand you
have a defraction grading of of um
distance comparable or smaller to the
wavelength of the radiation the the
fraction grading will spread it out all
over the
place so it's it's not just electrons
electrons photons uh
anything okay uh if there are no other
questions I'm going to go home and find
out if my son had his baby
yet okay
for more please visit us at stanford.edu